software engineering radio episode 107
Andrew Watson on the object Management
Group this is software engineering radio
the podcast for professional developers
on the web at s e - radio dotnet se
radio prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every 10 days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our website for supporting the hot
rod
[Music]
welcome listeners to another episode of
software engineering radio this is
another episode we were recalling a
torpedo in 2008 and we're of course
thankful to the Opie organizers for
giving us the little room which we can
use here in this episode we are going to
talk about the OMG what it does why it
exists and all that we are talking to
Andrew Watson why don't you introduce
yourself to our listeners you can do
that better than I can
thanks Marcus well I'm yes on my name's
Andrew Watson I'm vice president and
technical director of oMG object
Management Group which is one of these
organizations whose mission has changed
a little bit over the years so now we
tend to call ourselves oMG rather than
an object management group I guess if we
were renaming ourselves today we might
call ourselves something like the the
interoperability management group or
something like this because
interoperability and standards for
interoperability has become our key
focus in the last few years
yeah yeah it's like soap meaning of the
acronym has been delegated well and has
just has changed and so on yeah it's um
oMG was set up in the late eighties when
the enthusiasm about object was starting
to build the object for a technology
that had been in the laboratory places
like AT&T Bell Labs and Xerox PARC and
was starting to move into industry and
there was a determination amongst many
engineers that this history wasn't going
to repeat itself
they had just been burnt by the UNIX
wars UNIX was a technology that promised
to free the customer from lock-in to
proprietary operating system yep and of
course as soon as UNIX what happened the
marketplace it fragmented yeah and that
that phase is passed now of course we
have Linux and system 5 and standardized
API is but real while it looked as
though UNIX was going to be fragmented
and diluted when object technology
starts to get out of the market place
there was a group of determined
engineers who worked for a number of
software companies in the northeast of
the United States who wanted to make
sure that there were standards public
open standards object technology to
avoid the same thing happening and oMG
is still very strongly involved in
object technology of course and but we
no longer are completely limited to just
working with object I guess that's the
same fate if you want to call it like
that like for example the conference we
were at here it's called olp which
stands for object-oriented programming
well or okhla right so these have all
gone broader and objects have become
mainstream yet lately accepted as with
all of these quote revolutions it seems
to take a generation it seems to take
10-15 years for a good idea that's
emerging from the labs to become
mainstream and completely accepted um
and of course we're looking at the same
thing today with things like solar so R
is a technology that has got a lot of
press in the last two or three years but
in fact when you dig down you'll find it
so it's a very old idea yeah obviously
yes arguably I mean I worked on a
research project in Cambridge where I
live in the UK and in the early 90s and
arguably we were doing
I would definitely we were doing
service-oriented architecture then yeah
that was the answer project and in turn
we were building on even earlier
technology I've when I give my talks I
mention so a technology going back to
the late seventies but the important
point is not oh well you know we thought
of it first or somebody else thought of
it first the important thing is that sir
is a good idea which is now entering the
mainstream after a long period of being
carefully investigated and research and
the same is true of objects and there
are many other technologies and all of
them are obviously evolutions or
evolutionary developments on stuff that
has been there before at some point I
guess the community decides to give
something a new name maybe either
because it has changed change enough so
it should have a new name or just I
don't know for being able to to maybe
put it well to I bit a bit maybe but I'd
take a slightly more positive view it
just does take time for good ideas to
spread you know we're
all we all get a little set in our ways
we all carry on doing what we understand
what we know it just does take time or
good ideas for it to become recognized
their values become recognized them for
them for them to spread rollory is that
happily no bad ideas tend to die okay
let's let's briefly go back to the
beginnings of OMG so you said that the
goal was to make sure that the oh the
object technology doesn't recommend so
what was some of the first results of
for OMG did was what was one of the
first standards that people probably can
relate to well the first standard of
course that I'm sure a lot of people
wear was a thing called Koba and kuba is
a an object based middleware
specification it's a standard for
interoperability both between
applications and the middleware and
between separate instances of the
middleware they're running on several
platforms so that you should be able to
go out and buy Cobra implementations
from multiple vendors write applications
against the standard Corbray Beha api so
you know that your applications will be
portable between vendors and and also if
you buy from multiple vendors put a
vendor a's implementation on one machine
vendor some additional other have them
talk together yeah and Kolber has been
used in the past very widely in the
enterprise it still underlies enterprise
javabeans Eid baby there are a lot of
people who are using a JB are using uber
technology today without realizing it
and it's used very widely today in
real-time and embedded applications yeah
that's that's actually a focus I've seen
that the enterprise moves to the war WS
star stuff and and core bar goes to the
more technical embedded and it's being
used in some quite interesting and
surprising places you know Moore's law
tells us that the amount of CPU
permanent memory doubles every 18 months
so something which 15 years ago was an
enterprise and let's forget nice don't
forget corpora is 15 years old now yeah
someday which 15 years ago as an
enterprise scale system that you needed
a huge air-condition machine room to
hold today literally fits in the palm of
your hand
yes and so one of the applications where
Cobras being used today is in
software-defined radios the US military
found itself with I think over a hundred
separate
radios were being used in different
branches of the Navy the Marines the Air
Force and so on and it was getting to
the point where if one vehicle needed to
interact with aircraft and ground
vehicles and and soldiers and it needed
to carry several radio sets and it was
getting to be a literally a problem
fitting the mobile in into the vehicle
particularly an aircraft so it took a
very brave decision a couple of years
ago to put a bar on buying hardware
radio standard radios where the
performance the radios determined purely
by hardware and to switch to
software-defined radios where software
running either on general-purpose
processors or an exotic DSPs FPGAs and
but anyway software that can be loaded
in in the field defines the behavior of
the radio so one radio could not only
have its personality that change very
quickly by loading a new what the the
software radio people call waveform it's
a shorthand for all the software that I
do yeah I'm loading a new waveform into
radio can change its personality very
quickly but also one radio can have
multiple waveform there did at once and
so that you can get to a situation where
one device can load several of 100
different waveforms and talk
simultaneously to satellites aircraft
and ground vehicles now the US military
are spending a startling sum of money on
this I I can't remember the numbers of
top of my head but it is measured in
billions of dollars um and inside every
single one of those software-defined
radios that they're acquiring is korba
maybe they've built the interoperability
standards for the multiple processes
within the radio right Bible SiC
processes inside the handset or the or
the vehicle radio all talk to each other
using korba based interfaces although
corbera is one of these technologies
we've always said that middleware is
like plumbing and good if you don't see
it yes exactly you know you don't
remember that you've got plumbing until
you come downstairs one morning and find
the kitchen is knee-deep in water and
you remember yeah I have plumbing and
guess what it stopped working so
similarly middleware is one these things
we don't really notice it until this
stops working and this is a great
illustration of that it'll be inside all
those software-defined radios and nobody
who's using them will have any idea
there another standard well let me let
me continue the story chronologically so
yes and the in the late eighties
we worked on Cobre and related
specifications standardized some
services essentially Cobra was was the
foundation of a service-oriented
architecture oMG has 15 years of
experience with this um and then in the
mid 90s we act as a forum for brokering
agreement in the object oriented
analysis and design world if you were
paying attention to what was going on
there in the mid-90s and I have to admit
I wasn't but if you think yeah well I'm
sure yes young fresh face tablet you are
and there were probably about half a
dozen different visual
design notations that had been designed
through the early nineties by different
authors who were keen to have a way of
visually representing designs for object
software objects on it was new we needed
new notations for representing these
designs and many of these these
notations very good but of course they
were all different they've been designed
in isolation and the net result was
there was little uptake people customers
were confused they didn't know which one
to use no if they were reluctant to
invest heavily and using any one of them
for fear that their investment would be
lost if that notation stopped being used
not being supported um Eva Jakob Tsin
who was at Ericsson at this time
estimated I came up with the figure of I
think a couple of million dollars a year
but Ericsson could be spending on
documenting their designs using an
object-oriented design notation and of
course they picked the wrong one that's
several million dollars worth of
investment that comes so much scrap
paper if you can no longer find people
who understand the diagrams or buy tools
that could implement them so customers
were confused there was not much of a
market in the tooling hmm again right as
opposed to fragment in it the whole
market was vulcanized and a couple of
things happened in the mid-90s which we
helped broker first of all of course
three of the leading exponents of object
based design came together as a single
company rational the so called three
amigos
yakusan boot and rumba and secondly OMG
put out what we call an RFP or a better
proposals one of our documents that
starts a standardization process or
visual modeling and between these two
influences between the the initial
grouping at rational and this the
activity that OMG started through the
mid-90s we achieved standardization of
what today we know as UML your mother's
changed a little bit over the years
there are early versions irrational that
were called UML and the thing that OMG
adopted was
noticeably different and and
incidentally we did have a bit of a a a
dilemma there should we call the OMG
specification UML as the three amigos
had generously given us the rights to do
even though it was a little bit
different
it was notably different to what they
had created there or should we recognize
that it was a new development and give
it a new name and risk losing all the
brand recognition of the UML name had
built up so we in the end as you know we
stayed with the UML name but it is
important to recognize the contributions
that many other people 20 organizations
contributed to the UML 1 specification
it not just a rubber stamping of the
excellent work the three amigos did and
the result from about ninety seven was
we had UML one right now of course we
have UML - but even UML one had a
dramatic effect on the market and this
day I'm a standards guy I work for
standards organization I believe in what
I do and I will at the drop of a hat
stand up at the pulpit and preach the
sermon of standards and my text is taken
from a story of UML because before the
UML standard came along the market was
fragmented that basically wasn't a
market in their own visual design tools
and the techniques weren't being used
although they were all good after the
creation of the UML standard the mere
existence of the standard created a
unified market and that market grew at
about twenty percent a year
brew the the turn of the millennium for
about ninety nine 2002 even as the wider
IT market went into recession into the
command so and I'll just finish my point
here the important point is not that UML
is necessarily technically better than
what went before it and we can have that
argument here and there are people here
at this conference who would who would
argue you know tell you all about your
males floors and I'm happy to admit that
UML like any like any standard certainly
there are always things that were could
be improved it's not there's necessarily
better it's the fact of a single
standard 3/8 marketplaces
standardization does not destroy
competition it does not destroy
innovation
on the contrary it acts as a springboard
for healthy competition and innovation
in a market like this it's been very UML
is very very encouraging story for us
against many of the criticism and I'm
also often criticizing UML for certain
things the criticism isn't necessarily
that it's a bad language the criticism
is more that it's quote misused
so I mean UML was built for certain
things and it was not built for certain
other things and for certain other
things that might be better solutions I
mean for example if you look at the
Medicaid spoke for example who like the
barium Helen they're 10 times better
than email I guess for what they're
doing they really are better than the
email so I think one of the dangers of
standards and I experience it every day
if I work with my customers and talk
about domain-specific languages as
opposed to UML is that as soon as there
is a standard people use it for things
for which it wasn't initially thought to
be used and for which it maybe isn't
necessarily suitable XML it's the same
thing so I think that's that's a big
argument
what should you use it for and what you
should maybe not use it for and again it
comes down to something we mentioned
earlier you know if if you're good at
one technology if you understand one
technology you do tend to apply it to a
lot of things right maybe sometimes the
things that it's not not applicable to
the old expression you know if you have
a hammer everything looks like a nail
yeah um but nevertheless UML has been
designed to be flexible and you
mentioned domain-specific languages OMG
has separately from UML standards to
help us build domain-specific languages
a modeling framework but oh and UML is
built on I think oh is it now called
modeling framework morph or is it still
master morph actually sounds for
objective change right but I refer to as
a modeling framework because that's what
it is it's a framework or it can be used
as a framework for building modeling
languages and oMG has built several
other modeling languages using this same
modeling framework we have a couple that
I'd like to mention later on in this
podcast bpmn the business process
modeling notation is being moved on to a
moth platform
SBV r is a completely
language for expressing the semantics of
business vocabulary and rules and is
gaining is attracting a lot of interest
in the business community as a way of
formally documenting simple things like
the meanings of words it sounds very
straightforward but one of the major
sources of confusion I have found in my
work on and as a specification over the
years is just disagreement on the work
what the words mean and I'm sure you've
had the same experience you have those
those interminable arguments that last
for days where nobody seems to eat the
other guy just seems to be spouting
gibberish well no actually he's using
all the right words but what he's saying
doesn't make sense then you realize
after a couple of days oh your
definition of no this term one batter is
subtly different to my definition of one
bad and therefore all the other
misunderstandings flow from that
SBV are is a specification which will
help businesses come up with precise
definitions of you know if you're a car
rental company exactly what a rental
agreement is exactly what a customer is
house a bit like ontology yes yes and
another specification that OSBI was
related to that OMG is working on is an
ontology definition metamodel which will
then help us to relate work done in SPV
are where they work done in our RDF and
and common logics and so on and the OD
mmm is also based on my I guess the
object definition metamodel yes we
actually call it OD m some there
sometimes a little inconsistent you're
right sometimes mmm is metamodel and
sometimes we just use one but yes OD m
is also based on off this is one of oh
em gee s great ortho slightly hidden
strengths right now yeah we're doing a
lot of work on creating a lot of
modeling related specifications but is
all based almost on the common ba
framework which is of course then
strongly related to what Eclipse is
doing with the MF era open source
implementations oh well oh yeah I mean
that's one of those things right there
is morph seem off a morph PMF and none
of them is exactly the same yes we do
I'm happy to say
we're not happy to say I'm happy to
admit that we we do have an issue there
but again it's one we're moving to
address we're organizing in March at
Eclipse condo we have a full day's
symposium on alignment between our
energy specifications and and eclipse
open source software and anybody who's
interested in that do please come along
and participate it's gonna be an open
open forum we don't want to work out how
we can bring oMG specifications and a
clipped open source software a pleasant
into alignment we're also going to run a
version of the same symposium at the or
Bush part 2 of the same symposium at B
oMG meeting in Ottawa in June an open
invitation anyone who's interested in
making things better in this area he's
come along but maybe make sure that
we've put this podcast online before
those days okay yes I thought you put
the beautiful see down there okay I'll
cut it out so so yeah so I think from my
perspective
Moff is much more useful than UML
because a meta standard that helps you
to define languages and that therefore
makes tools for language definition
interoperable is in my view much more
useful than let's say implying a
standardized modeling language but
that's just my background so I'm
obviously not saying that that that's
necessarily true but I have much more
interest in more than and then in UML
because well the model driven work it's
more important yeah and but but to come
back on that it does it does lead into
an interesting point
people get attached to syntax mm-hmm I
have this theory that every programming
language is great for the next few years
exactly exactly you have the point is
cursed to have syntax that's slightly
reminiscent of c-plus every because that
means that you can hand that language
over to somebody new and they'll be able
to write the hello world program and get
it to run within half an hour or an hour
and once you can do that you've got them
the fact that the underlying semantics
may be completely different might take
them weeks to learn there for instance
you know Java and C++ underlying object
model underlying model is very different
but you can take a C++ programmer and
give him the job a bookie and have hello
world running in and inside an hour and
you've got him emotionally you've got
him if you give him a wonderful new
language with a completely new syntax
that takes weeks to learn he's probably
not going to get over that learning
curve now my point but I'm coming to is
UML has had the same influence and every
and not everybody uses UML but people
who invent new domain-specific languages
which is you know I've had certain no
criticism of that but what they often do
quite reasonably is create them with UML
like syntax and they explain them as
well you know this is a lot like UML
class diagram except it's different in
these ways so UML's influence is
destined to be a lot wider than just the
people who use UML per se I think a lot
of people are going to be using notation
that is reminiscent of UML lots of
different jobs when they create their
domain-specific languages and
incidentally um no RMG as provided in
UML a mechanism a simple mechanism for
building domain-specific languages that
are closely allied to UML the so called
profile mechanism err I'd Susie it's
been used I you know yoga I can see
there's a little bit of skepticism
across the table here but look at sysml
yes SML is proving very successful it's
strongly based on your melon it's
entirely defined using using UML's
profile mechanism no I mean I mean we
shouldn't spread his argument forever
and and then obviously UML has a huge
impact on people to sketch this cast
talk about systems yep clearly no
question and also it's good to have a
standard especially in systems
engineering where you
five million vendors and like like you
know supply chains and everybody needs
to agree on something that's completely
given nope or no question the the
profile making mechanism I well I know
that it can do everything in theory tool
support for it is limited so the the the
the things you can actually do is
limited and then there is another I
think problem with it and that is that
if you have a profile your my model even
if you have your own domain specific
profile what you get out of your tool X
my export or something it's still
extremely complex because you cannot
take anything away from the UML at least
not on the let's say ast level so there
are limitations and so so so so yeah I'm
and and it's important to say I'm
turning not claiming that UML is an
answer the answer to every problem some
people do like to set up I mean it maybe
looks good in magazine articles you know
but somehow there's this battle is this
this battle royal between on the one
hand you know the UML zealots and on the
other hand the domain-specific language
enthusiasts it's not like that there's a
spectrum yes I know one end of the
spectrum of people who for perfectly
legitimate business reasons want to use
a completely standardized language and
will restrict themselves just using
empty standard you amount and then we
move through the people who will
customize UML a bit using using profiles
all the way to the people who want again
for perfectly legitimate business
reasons to create an entirely new
domain-specific language that particular
domain no I don't want to sound smug but
the great thing about OMGs modeling
offering us at the moment is we can
support everybody on that spectrum
I say we and the OMG community that the
community of utilization made uses oMG
special maybe through your mouth yeah so
one end of spectrum we have the UML
specification at the other end if you
want to go out and build a complete new
domain-specific language both provides
you with with tooling to do that yeah
okay since we're already talking about
some of that modeling stuff
why don't you mention the MDA standard I
guess everybody knows what it's all
about but why don't we discuss the
current status the sub standards that
are applicable and what their statuses
well MDA model-driven architecture is
it's really more of an initiative under
standard rights a family of standards
would point it's as you said a lot of
people use modeling notations the
sketching for communication that's fine
but we can if we use modeling notations
precisely we can extract quite a lot of
information about system design from
them and use it at the very least to
build the framework of an implementation
and it's very we very careful not to
over promise on MDA some people happen
initially a little bit at least between
the lines it didn't come from Angela
it's not a lot of saying but between the
lines that were a lot of like you know
like I think about something at press
the MDA button and but that didn't come
from I'm very careful right from the
beginning to make sure that we weren't
promising IT nirvana where you go out
draw a couple of diagrams that represent
the system press a button and a working
system pops out of Iraq um but even with
quite crude modeling notations and UML
one wasn't designed for MDA and had to
be adapted a little bit to make it work
UML to incidentally is a lot better one
of the design points P or mailto was to
clean up the underlying metamodels to
make it more compatible with MDA but
even with it with UML one it was
possible to build tools which would spit
out function frameworks and database
schemas and so on and that would
probably write 30 40 percent of your
code and the tedious code as well not
the interesting business lobby but all
that you know the tedious and interface
definitions and database definitions and
so on and the glue code and
incrementally as the tooling has got
better the percentage of your
application that you can get out of M da
tools
as has increased over the last few years
the impressive thing for me is zooming
back looking at the big picture there
was a study from Walt Disney World that
we had a couple of years ago these guys
wrote two parts of one of their billing
applications using different
technologies it wasn't a fully
controlled study but it was close on the
one hand you had a team who were using a
good traditional programming environment
with Java of course and on the other
hand you had a team that was using a
suite of MDA tools good MDA tools but
not leading-edge
and two things first of all the people
who were using the MDA tool were three
times more productive they wrote three
times more lines of code per dollar
spent than the people who are using the
non MDA technique so you're looking at
greater productivity or you guys at the
sharp end the program yeah
but for me more impressive was the bug
right the bug rates in the code that had
been generated
yeah we've been based using MDA
technique were one third those
encountered in traditional hand coding
so of course in both ways of creating
applications you can still get the
design wrong and if you've got a design
wrong then the implementation will be
wrong yeah but when you code by hand
there's another step where you co you
can jacked errors you can take a correct
design and just make a coding error yeah
MDA doesn't eliminate that of course but
it reduces the scope for doing that and
we found this in several studies and
let's not forget that if you're building
a successful system which we all despise
to do building successful system
anything up to 90% of the cost of owning
it total cost of owning at over its
entire life that might be ten twenty
years ninety percent of that cost is
post implementation there it's training
the people who use it and training them
is harder if the systems buggy sure you
know oh you do this you do that and then
you do that but if this happens then you
have to work around it by doing this and
you have to train people for 20 years to
say oh and if that particular error
message happens you have to work around
like this that bugs not there it's
cheaper to train the people to use it
you don't have to fix the bugs there was
nothing so be the biggest impact I feel
that model driven techniques will have
on software is not the in
initial productivity of creating the
system that useful
it's the increasing of the quality of
the system exactly and therefore the
reduced total cost of ownership over
there likely that will dominate all
other effect there and and to that I
should mention one of the other
initiatives that part of MDA is a thing
called architecture driven modernization
which humorously turns out to be MDA
backwards ADM and the ADM specifications
are important because if we're going to
be using MDA to create systems we have
to recognize that nobody has a
Greenfield application if everybody
who's writing code today almost no I
think it's fair to say without exception
has to interface with other code that's
already out there
legacy system isn't isn't it fun funny
we refer to legacy systems are so
they're some quaint holdover from a
previous age well it's everything that's
already out there everything that's
already out there and by golly there's a
lot of it you know estimates are that
application engineers across the
software industry collectively spend
more than 50% of their time maintaining
old applications for any legacy
application so it's important to have a
way when we're creating applications
using MDA it's important to have a way
of interfacing them with the existing
applications ADM standards are about be
certainly very difficult job of trying
to pull design information out of old
applications where no design exists and
nobody again again it's important to
emphasize nobody's claiming that you
throw a heap of code an ad a mental
stress Department and a perfect UML
diagram pops out the Trump this is
always going to be a process where a
skilled engineer as cool assistant so
rather than the tool doing all the work
but it is vital that we have ways of
extracting designs from old code so that
model-driven techniques can then help us
build new code that interfaces with the
old note but that's a very important
part of the MDA snoring and the ADM is
finalized or is it in the place well ADM
is actually the name of a group inside
oMG that is working on a number of
specification Co their first one is a
thing called KDM which is knowledge
definition Metamora and that's a
standard metamodel of sand a set of
concepts for representing aspects of
software design
they've got a lot of work ahead of them
in in ADM to work on more more
specifications representing more parts
of the desert reverse engineering
process but but we've made a start
an interesting spin off from that has
been into Software Assurance people who
do Software Assurance to look at
off-the-shelf applications and try to
work out I mean say you're again come
comes back to the military you know you
you've got a drive in the US military
for buying more software off-the-shelf
great costs come down quality is
probably just as good except you're paid
to be a little bit paranoid and you want
to make sure nobody's put any backdoors
in this case how do you do that mm-hm
software assurance efforts
ah there to test existing software to
make sure that it works within some
specified set of criteria including
security criteria they are no backdoor
so no covert knows and it turns out it's
a very similar problem to reverse
engineer right because you have to
understand what's going up to understand
what's going on so there's a group that
has spun off inside oMG from the
alkylation of modernization group that
just looking at using similar standards
ADM standards for software modernization
and the good news from our point of view
is because of this drive using more
off-the-shelf software in governments
and so on around the world and there's
now a lot of government money around to
say well now we bought this software
help us help us be assured that it does
the right thing yeah it's an interesting
area interesting spin-off that I
personally hadn't really hadn't foreseen
you mention a couple of the more
specific standards that the ADM folks
are working on so what are some of the
more specific standards what MDA
comprises and what's the status of them
well the other things that we're doing
as part of the MDA program are several
specifications to do with models and
moff once you've captured your design
using UML or another modeling language
once you come to design them off
framework MDA foundation of MDA is about
transforming those models into other
forms are then extracting information
from them and using it to create and
whatever it whatever it is
'mother schemas and so on yeah well yes
ultimately everything is a model but at
some point you want to get to a model
that's represented as C code right or a
database schema so a couple of useful
specifications then I'll just touch on
these efforts very good there's thing
called Oh qvt which stands for query
view and transforms which is a suite of
specifications under one standard for
transforming both models into other mock
models it's important to say in each of
these cases just because oMG is
standardizing something it's absolutely
not the case and this is something that
was impossible before we aim there not
to innovate with our standards we aim
not to be doing research
this criticism that that omg's that
aren't always pragmatic but let's touch
on that later I go we can come breaking
it's just touched my soul touching it
now okay okay it's it's a fine balance
to strike if you've got an emerging area
of interest such as how you transform a
model to another model um if you create
the standard too early you're taking
research and you're codifying it as a
standard and that's likely to be a
disaster
give it your relational a bit has that
smell a little bit it's you know we we
revised our standards so if we see that
there's there's an issue and people
feedback problems yes you know we these
problem many of our specifications is
perfect and I of course well sort of a
diversion of an eye version I should I
should mention here that if anybody
comes across problem with one of our
specifications please please please do
get in touch with us and report it we
have a bug reporting process now we have
people whose job so called revision task
force's whose job is to maintain these
specifications we don't claim they're
perfect if you found a problem we want
to hear about it so we can fix it but
coming back to where was i coming back
to talk about QED yes it took about DVT
and so qbt is the set of specifications
for how you transform models into into
other models something that certainly
MDA tools have been doing for some years
now seems like the right time to
standardize this so that if we've
created a set of transforms in then
there's tool you have a chance of being
able to pull them to vendors bender
Bea's tool we're just currently with
most mainstream tools not the case so I
think yes yeah and and implementations
are qvt are we just starting now it's
most of them are operational yeah as we
set all these things and when O&B
publishes the specification it can then
take a couple of years for it to get
into a large number of tools there will
typically be a couple of implementations
around a publication on but but it'll
take a couple years get into into large
numbers so qvt is one important MDA
related specification mauve model to
text is another one that's a
specification for standardized ways of
taking more
bottles and turning them into arbitrary
text like Percy programs database
schemas and so on and and there are
several other initiatives around around
mauve the standardizing the workings
under the bonnet as we brits would say
or under the hood as the Americans would
say under the under the bonnet of of MDA
other work that we're doing is in the
area of other modeling languages I've
mentioned a couple of them appr BPMN is
an interesting one yep BPM in his
business process modeling notation yeah
unlike UML UML is a spam a family of 13
or so depending on exactly how you count
yeah but some around 13 different
notations yeah bpmn is a single notation
for drawing business processes and it's
specifically been designed to be to be
usable by and friendly to the business
user if some business users are a bit
intimidated by your mouth it just seems
to block their to behavior um bpmn has
been designed so that a business analyst
can sit down maybe with a programmer or
maybe even an end-user somebody who
actually you know maj from accounts but
actually actually works through the
process of filing accounts can sit down
and say okay when i finally how do i do
this this and this new document in ppm n
in a way this very readable is like a
flow chart with swim lanes but at the
same time precise enough that we can
extract information from it use it to
inform an MDA prisoners bpmn was
originally designed by a thing called
BPM i business process modeling
initiative and wasn't initially based on
law and so one of the things we're doing
at the moment through another BP
standard just as all the standards in
web services are called ws something so
all the standards know mg to do with
business processes are called BP
something yeah so another BP standard
his BP DM business process definition
metamodel and this is brand new within
the last couple of months
it's a standard metamodel or
representing business processes so that
even if you've used other business
process representation languages you can
map them all onto a common etymology
though they the long term goal here is
that BPMN or more specifically a second
version of bpmn will map onto B PDM the
business process definition metamodel
which in turn is built on mauve to give
us this same path from diagrams to
models that we've already got in the UML
corner of MDA so we're I think one of
the strongest areas of growth at the
moment nobody among the most exciting
areas is the work on business process
standard another specification that
working on at the moment which is
somewhat outside the MDA dream is BPM M
the business process maturity model this
is a new departure for OMB because this
is not a model in the Senate in the
Morrison yeah this is a model in the CMM
CMM sense yeah this is about how mature
how repeatable how well-documented are
your business processes so just as CMM
is about making sure that software
organizations have well-defined ways of
writing software which then helps you to
ensure that the quality of the software
is good
so BPM M is about making sure that your
business has well-defined ways well
defined procedures for doing all the
things that it does it you know it could
be a procedure for hiring a new employee
it could be a procedure for billing a
client know you know your business
typically has hundred of these processes
are often carried around in the heads of
the people who execute the business
um BPM M if if we're to have a hope of
automating businesses more we have to
make sure that the business understands
what it does yeah as we as we're
software engineers all know that the
number one course cause of software
disasters is you go to the business
people they tell you what they think
they want you implement it you go back
to them and said here's what you said
you wanted and they say well that's not
what we wanted right because
either they didn't understand what they
did or somewhere in the communication
between them and you something got lost
so having good documentation of what the
business actually does is important
before you can provide an implementation
software that does that and in turn BPM
M will help business analysts going into
organizations who want the document what
the organization does there will help
them to essentially make her judgment as
to you know whether the organization
even knows that if there's one person
buried somewhere deep in the bowels of
the organization who knows who's the
only person who knows what you do when
this set of events happen and he's never
been written down the chances of an
analyst or a designer going in to
implement that process finding out what
happens when this particular exception
occurs they're essentially zero no BPA
memory I think again as a analog for CMM
before the processes it could be quite
important now so um why don't we briefly
look at how M dmg actually does the
standardization process I I've once
heard the statement that probably it's
not really true but it was really funny
which was an OMG standard is a political
statement masking as a software standard
well how does it work how does it work
um first of all there's always politics
even when you're building an application
inside a single company there's always
politics so people say you know and
criticize us for politics being involved
my challenge anybody who's been involved
in any large project yeah show me a
project as Priya vortex
rating OMG standards is about brokering
agreement it's about making sure that
all the people who have a stake in the
game who are going to be implementing
tools that implement these specification
are happy enough and unfortunately there
is always going to be a degree of
compromise as there is in everything in
real life so what oMG does and I guess
this is really reduced to its
fundamentals well what I do what my job
is is to broker agreement between the
stakeholders and help them write the
common specification that is that meets
enough of all their requirements that is
going to be useful to them and and it is
a social process
the way the OMG process works is we
start out by building a small community
inside oMG people are interested in
particular area there might be only
three or four people and they writes a
call to arms to the industry a thing
called a request for information which
is sent out widely as we can it
essentially says you know oMG and thinks
that there's a need for a common
standard in this area please comment it
sent out to anybody around you member or
not and we then works with the comments
and the the RFI has two purposes one to
to gather information and two to gather
more recruits so hopefully we get to the
situation where we've got a nucleus of
domain expert working inside a group of
oMG and I should emphasize that although
we've been talking about what oMG terms
platform standards which are usable
across the entire software industry if
we also have a large group of domain
standard HR standards we used only in a
single domain finance for instance is a
good example we've just been working on
payment interoperability standards that
are very interesting to people in
finance banks credit card companies and
not not not going to be have much impact
at all outside that but inside that
industry very useful oh there is another
one healthcare example yes you've you've
done your homework we've got many of
these vertical domains and the process
works roughly speaking in the same way
both inside and outside these vertical
domains we build the group of people who
have a strong interest in this area and
they write essentially a requirements
document recalls requests for proposals
and even though it's typically only 30
or 40 pages long
that can take quite a long time because
part of it is building a shared
agreement over exactly what the
requirements are there we come back to
this issue we touched on earlier about
arguments over what the words mean okay
we try to get all the arguments over
what the words mean out of the way at
that stage you've left it until after
requirements gathering it's too late so
it can be quite a protracted process but
we build this RFP and there appears then
issued now
oMG is a large organization with
hundreds of members were international
but we're not a government organization
financed by member fine menos yep we're
a club essentially when uhm financed by
people who believe the standard thing
for the kinds of reasons I mentioned
earlier UML standard it builds markets
it it fosters innovation so but the
point on I'm getting to here is we have
no special exemption under antitrust
laws there are organizations that do but
we do not so what we can't do it as oMG
is go out once we got the requirements
document and say right company a Company
B Company C you've got the best
technology in this area we want you to
go out and write an OMG specifications I
am okay because if we did we'd be
building an anti-competitive cartel and
Company D who we hadn't invited could
quietly come back and sue us you know
both in Europe and in the US and in
several jurisdictions as well and it's
happened it hasn't happened to us but it
has happened to other organizations so
we're very careful at this point we
issue the RFP and then as far as oMG in
the narrowest sense of the word the ogen
organization IMG is concerned we just
sit and wait at that point now what's
actually happening is large numbers of
oMG members are organizing into groups
sometimes they submit singly but more
often they self organized into groups I
don't have any say over that I don't
want to you know it's outside for these
antitrust reasons and they create
proposals against this RFP and submit
them for evaluation back to oMG and that
proposal writing and submission back
happens outside our process so after a
few months we typically are looking at
one or more proposals from it's always
several several organizations it's very
very rare if you just get a single
company submitting a single repair and
the group of experts inside oMG which we
call a task or evaluates these proposals
the task force will certainly include
end-users the the submitters
often have a couple of end-users but
it's fair to say that they're often um
outnumbered by the vendors of the tools
yeah but this is an important balance
when you're creating specifications you
must listen to both the people who will
create implementations and the people
who'll use them if you only listen to
one of those two groups what you produce
is not going to be used by the opener so
we have an evaluation and then we go
around this loop typically once or maybe
twice more the submitters revise their
proposal in the light of the evaluation
and then resubmit and is then
re-evaluated and when we get to the
stage where both the evaluators and the
submitters are happy which can take a
couple of iterations and it then goes
through it's been voted on by the task
force and recommended to the rest of our
jury now at this point a thing called
the architecture board as it's a OMG has
a
fairly powerful and certainly very
highly skilled group of individuals will
be architects board they're elected by
the rest of oMG by an open democratic
process but very proud of the fact that
Oh everything in oMG is done by an open
and fully documented vote you know it
may be a bit political at times but it's
really democratic oh and the
architecture boards job is to make sure
that the work that's been done by this
one task force focusing on one area of
the whole technology spectrum is
nevertheless compatible with OMGs out
the work um so that for instance an
early job the architecture board did was
to ensure that UML and moth were
compatible and and it is a good job
there so I'll collect your board ensures
that the proposal is compatible other
proposals in in other technologies
related technologies and he's working on
and then the architecture board once
they've endorsed it recommends it the
whole of Mg and at this point typically
um the hard work is all over and we have
a couple more votes um and so the
reviews I guess and public reviews but
usually by the time the task force has
made a recommendation and the
architecture board has reviewed it and
is happy with it typically by that stage
the thing has really been through the
mill has been really thoroughly examined
and it is actually unheard of it's never
happened or specification to be then
defeated after after that although it
does still get widely reviewed and and
one specification was withdrawn rather
than defeated because it was it was seen
that it wasn't going to get widespread
public support but yeah it's then
published by omg um first of all as a
so-called beta specification which is
really intended for the tool vendors to
start implementing them and hopefully
feeding back any problems they find it
and then after a certain amount of time
as which might call a public beta we
then go to a full formal specification
and that's the stage where and we hope
that end-users will also start working
with it you don't publish a
compatibility test sued or something
so interoperability testing and
conformance testing is an interesting
issue yeah as I having you remember in
the beginning of MDA
basically every code generator called
itself I'm not saying you called them
but everybody basically called
themselves an MDA tool because it was
the password of the day and well well
that's success you know it's you know
when a lot of people want to be part of
your gang because it seems to be cool to
be part of your gang I guess that's my
bad sign yeah yeah but yeah no come back
the serious point interoperability
testing compliance testing against the
specifications is is very important and
it's something that I personally would
like to see us do more of yeah
the problem is it's also ferociously
expensive building a test suite
comprehensive test suite to test against
the specification is going to cost you
you know millions of dollars potentially
another approach would be to publish a
reference implementation like the Java
guys do I think that's quite useful
because you've proved that it works
yeah reference implementations I have a
slightly contrarian view on router
implementations let me let me give you
let me just talk around that the problem
with the reference implementation is
that there's a risk it will become the
only implementation you publish a
reference implementation which of course
is going to be optimized for just one
set of circumstances don't forget that
in OMG we're talking about interface
standards it's entirely down to the
vendors how they implement things that
are behind the interfaces and to look at
middleware for instance you could
implement middleware that was extremely
robust or you implement middleware that
was extremely fast or you could
implement middleware that was extremely
small or whether it's extremely scalable
other than on functional stuff basic all
the whole bunch of stuff and you're
going to be making trade-offs behind the
interfaces for different areas of
performance and so no one implementation
is going to meet all those different as
DIF requires if we had published a
reference implementation of Koba the
risk is that it would become the only
implementation and it would have a
certain sub trade-offs it would be
optimizing the being you know small or
fast or whatever and any bugs that it
had would become the render it become
the reference bugs yeah and unless your
behavior of your implementation was
exactly the same as the reference
implementations behavior people would
point the finger at you and say it's not
like the reference implementation you
must be wrong and you can argue till
you're blue in the face none
look at the standard the standard here
says you know this baby that doesn't cut
it with the customers and I've seen them
I've seen this years ago outside oMG I
worked on postscripts implementation
slightly frustrating business Adobe had
published the specification of what
PostScript should do but unless your
implementation did exactly what the
Adobe implementation did including all
the bugs where you could point the
places where the Adobe implementation
did this and the Adobe specification
said something different if you'd
implemented the specification you were
wrong because you didn't do what the
Adobe implementation did well and it was
very hard I'm not criticizing Adobe
there a valued member of oMG but it was
very hard to compete against the dhobi
because you had to basically do into all
circumstances exactly what the Adobe
parent Asian did and there's a risk that
just as the Adobe implementations of
reference implementation of PostScript
and and there were very few others so a
reference implementation of Corbeau
would have become the early
implementation now that's not an excuse
or the lack of compatibility compliance
test like I would I would like to see
more we did I have compliance testing
for CORBA I would like to see more
compliance testing program
specifications and the the only
defense I offer for their not being more
is that it is very expensive we're not a
wealthy organization we have we are
funded by our members on membership
contributions relatively inexpensive and
we don't have money okay what it takes
what it's going to take frankly is for a
very large customer maybe something like
a big oil company but I think probably a
government to a either insist that you
know there be a referent a compliance
test and funded and then insist that
that people who sell the products comply
with it to this customer yeah III think
I think that's that's frankly what it's
gonna take to get more more compliance
testing um it's the one pp if you gave
me three wishes a technical director of
energy today wish number one would
definitely be like wave a magic wand and
make compliance tests not reference
implementation here but compliance tests
exist that would be my number one way
yeah so do you want to give our
listeners an overview between maybe the
roles other organizations like oMG w3c
Oasis do they cooperate you know what's
the what's the what's the story there
yeah well organizations like Oasis w3c
oMG we all operate in very similar ways
you know those three I you know we're
essentially membership organizations
companies with a shared interest
cooperating in a public process to build
non mandatory standards and by
non-mandatory I mean that you know
nobody forces you to implement right
after HTML or an oasis recommendation or
one of our standards we're not because I
said we're not government data array
bots ezreal
we focus on different areas of the
overall spectrum of standardization and
and organizations with different sets of
skills and members of different
organizations often with a lot of
overlap of course a lot of w3c members
are also energy members versus Meniere's
typically w3c worked on on web related
stuff including of course updated web
2.0 RDF and so on respiration and oMG is
typically working only really I think
has most of the interesting modeling
work going on today in modeling
languages and also a lot of middleware
work not only Cober but I should also
mention a middleware specification
called DDS distribution service which is
used extensively in real time middleware
particularly in in ships right they
worship um so that's that's where IMG's
areas of expertise are little where
interoperability modeling um and oasis
started out of course focusing on on
document standards built in XML and is
now doing a lot of XML based work on on
representing knowledge in different
vertical domains in in different medical
industries we don't have a formal
cooperation or relationship and we do
have liaisons with these other
organizations but informally there's
quite a lot of discussion as all the
members I guess because make sure
certainly through the members the
members make sure that there isn't
duplication it's in nobody's interest
there these organizations tread on each
other's toes or try to see each other's
turf and and also we do have informal
contacts between the staff of the
organization's again making sure that we
that we don't duplicate duplicator
between them then you can think of them
as little interlocking pieces of the
overall public open standards jigsaw and
and something that we all value real
sharing common is open standards and
open in the sense that anybody can
download them anybody can use them so
checked to the fact that we can't
guarantee and then this perhaps again is
just worth touching on we can't
guarantee the view implements now mg
standard you won't be infringing
somebody's patent somewhere oh yeah we
do our best to find out if there are any
patent software patents you would have
to license in order to implement no he's
specification and if we find them we do
document that part and but we can't
guarantee that there isn't somebody you
know in the vast tracts list EF of
Russia you know he's going to pop up
tomorrow waving a master patent on some
something that we didn't know about and
and that also is true incidentally of W
space the other races as well though but
openness in the case of all three
organizations openness and sharing
information is the name of the game and
there are analogies with the open
software open source software movement
and it's again you know we we all
believe that it benefits everybody and
we all know we all will benefit from the
work that is done creating these open
specifications no software to wrap this
up slowly but surely you mentioned
before the BPM and stuff so this hints
at the fact that you're also a zomg
working in the solar space yes or is
there more stuff in this so ah in a
environment or area that OMG is involved
in well there's a say sort of drawing
wrapping this type drawing ions right
one of the things that I feel quite
strongly at the moment is that there is
a synergy and a convergence between
these three areas of technology that
some people might see as separate
service oriented architecture
business process modeling and BPM
technology in general and MDA we feel
quite strongly in OMG that SOA is very
useful we've been working in SOA for
years and it's a useful way of
structuring your software to make it
flexible it's useful way of structuring
your business to make it flexible and
and as an aside I'd just like to mention
there is a separate organization
affiliated with IMG called the solar
consortium and the solar consortiums
mission is to promote and enable
business agility by a service-oriented
architecture but for our businesses to
compete innovate and thrive reading from
their mission statement there and and
the one of the things the so consortium
is trying to get across is that sir is
not just a way of building software yeah
it's it can also be a way of structuring
all of your business activities to make
them more flexible though a consortium
is is proving to be quite successful
Gartner is working with us on
publicizing and working on the snow
consortium and our consortium has had
quite a lot of exposure through Gartner
conference business very interesting but
anyway to return to the major thrust and
so our BPM and model driven approaches
so it can provide a framework for
building a flexible organization BPM can
provide the way of documenting what the
organization can do MDA is the vital
bridge between the two if we're going to
build flexible organizations we need to
be able to reconfigure our business
processes quickly to be able to say are
we where an insurance company can t
resell this service but we want to be
able to sell that service we'll need to
use all of our existing underwriting and
billing and so on services but put them
to go in a slightly different way and be
able to document the new process using
business modeling languages and then
automatically
reduce the glue code of choreograph
services to deliver the new service
quickly using model driven techniques I
think that's going to be a lot a very
powerful sweet spot yes and that
actually is going to be the subject of
my talk this afternoon here at the okay
very good
so to wrap this up you probably don't
know but anyway I have something in
common and that's we were both glider
pilots and so last weekend was actually
quite nice here in Germany we had strong
winds so we could do quite some rich
soaring like with 180 kilometers per
hour running her along the rich and
steep turns and stuff very funny so when
was your last flight ah yes I've been
I've been flying gliders for 15 years or
something like that now but like you I
was flying last weekend I live in
Cambridge in the UK which is that land
it's in the middle of cornfields and
it's winter at the moment so but
typically in the summer in those flat
lands you get good thermals as we call
them columns of warm rising air the
clouds come flying no thermals in the
winter so to avoid standing around in a
flat muddy field in the middle of
Cambridge I jumped in the car and I
drove 300 kilometres north to a place
called Southern Bank in Yorkshire and
just like you that's where you were
that's a place with a ridge and when the
wind blows onto the ridge then you'd be
rising air on the ridge you can use to
stay in the air but there's also a kind
of lift you get there called wave and
wave is is magical Anna marks you've
flown in wave along once been 7000
meters over Switzerland yes yeah so it's
it is it's it's like a magic carpet ride
but what happens is as you know the wind
blows over mountains and it sets up a
standing wave in the air that actually
goes much higher than the mountains so
there's a fairly low range of hills up
the backbone of England called the pen
irons only about three four hundred
meters for five hundred meters high but
on Saturday the conditions were just
ride the wind was blowing over the pen
irons it was setting up the standing
wave and we were flying two to three
thousand meters in the wave with a
beautiful view of the North England
which T both coasts and on other days
you know
in America in the rock is I'm sure it's
the same with you I've been to can't
convert meters but 22,000 feet but would
that be that would be six or seven
thousand seven thousand meters yes on
oxygen looking at the view looking down
on the airliner a lot of people think
that gliding is just you know you go up
and you come straight down it might be
surprised to know that the world out
you'd record in gliding is forty-nine
thousand feet it's fifteen kilometres
between kilometres above the surface and
people even in Britain which is you know
relatively small island people have
learned thousand kilometres in the
glider and as people die it's very fun
so to all you engineers out there let me
let me recommend the sport of gliding to
you because as engineers as a British a
British expression now if I'd be able to
translated definition of an engineer an
engineer is somebody who can do for 10
Bob what any damn fool can do for a
pound so and engineer somebody who can
do for 50 euro sense what any damn fool
can do for euro and engineers are fond
of optimization and getting something
for nothing
well lighting is getting something for
nothing you pay no money you use the
power of the Sun to keep you in the air
and fly long distances lots of lots of
lighter pilots wreden ears and it's
fairly cheap actually yes it's not more
expensive than playing tennis or
something yeah so if you don't buy your
own glider and then you've attacked with
a club it's actually fairly if if you've
never tried lighting it's definitely one
of those things that you owe yourself
is there a vertigo yeah theatres for you
in Germany you can fly solo as a glider
pilot at 16 15 14 UK 14 although you can
get the licence with 16 but yes and we
can't fly solo with nothing in Britain
you can fly solo at 16 which is younger
than you can drive right there so we've
got kids flying gliders around our
airfield in Cambridge who haven't got
their driving licenses yet but their
solo glider pilots already it's not
difficult to learn and it's a lot of
them probably the best thing you can do
with your spare time and although it is
addictive so you have yes but but also
I'm sure it's to say with you like any
addicts were also pushes we're always
trying to get new people hook absolutely
okay Andrew thank you very much for
being on the show
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and /not
buttons to contact the team leaves an
email to team at SU radio net or if it's
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license
please see the website for details
thanks to Charlie crowd and the pot site
Music Network for the music used in this
show the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]